Hello and welcome through another walkthrough
for computer architecture for everybody.
In this walkthrough I am going to walk
through the building of a slightly more
complex circuit. In this case we are going
to build a NAND gate. So NAND of course is
um the opposite of and so if both things are
one inputs are one the output is zero. And if
either any of the outputs are zero they're the
output is one. It's the opposite of of and. Um,
and so let's take a look at the picture. So the
way this works is there are two inputs and there
is a set of POS transistors at the top kind of
in parallel going from the positive voltage to
a common wire in the middle to out. And then there
is a set of NOS transistors in series between the
out and the ground. So the the just because this
is CMOS circuitry, the goal is to either have VDD
come out or ground to come out depending on A and
B in the combination based on the truth table. So
let's go ahead and draw this. So I'm going to
draw this in a little more traditional way than
I did on my previous demonstration. It's pretty
common to just draw a line across the top and
put the VCC across the top. So you see that
we're sort of emulating a lot of what these
uh diagrams look like. And then what I want to
do is I want to create some two P transistors.
So the A and the B. And so I'm going to drop
a little bit of of of P dope silicon down. I'm
going to give myself plenty of space and make
these plenty long. Okay. And then I'm going to
make some transistors there by putting some poly
across. I'm going to put it like I'm going to keep
this really tiny for now. Okay. So, there's
some poly. So, there's two transistors. So,
we just made by crossing the pdope silicon and the
polysilicon twice, we now have transistors that we
can hook A and B up to. We'll wire them up later.
Um, and then what we're going to do is we're going
to take the makes the output. I'll just make
the output be a horizontal piece of metal wire.
Now I've got to put some VAS in here so I can
connect the poly the pope silicon to the metal
where I need to. So let's put a punch a couple of
VAS in. Via via via via. So now the orange pope
silicon and the metals are connected. Okay. So the
next thing we need to do is we need to make some
NOS transistors down at the bottom. So, let's
grab some endope silicon and hook this up here.
And then,
oops, I need to fix that. I need to erase that.
I need to give myself a little space here. So,
I want to make some endope silicon that kind of
comes down from the center wire a little bit.
Um, and then I am going to make some more endope
silicon. Actually, I don't know if I need to do
that. Let's try to make it in one big piece of
endope silicon. Let me make my end dope silicon
longer. And now let's put some piece polysilicon
in to make two more transistors. So, we're going
to put transistor here and then another transistor
here. So, that's two transistors. There is a two
NOS transistors that are right there. And um
I think I might as well put my ground in now.
The ground down here. Traditionally, you sort of
draw that as a long horizontal line. I will place
some zero or ground voltage and then I'll place
a couple of VAS to make sure to connect the green
endop endop silicon to the metal in both of the
places. So, I think we mostly have this except
now we've got to take our inputs and connect them
to those transistors. So, let's make an A input
for now. Let's make a little bit of metal. This
shouldn't be too hard. So, let's just say this is
our A input. And then we're going to hook that to
here. Uh, I want to make that a little longer. So,
I'm going to make my pink a little bit longer. I'm
going to put a on this one, which is a little bit
different. Yeah. So, I'm going to bring the pink.
So, here's the thing. I can paint this pink. So,
now I have an overlap. See how I painted that
pink? So, it overlaps with a metal now. So,
I can pop a pop a via in there. Punch. Punch. So,
that is um my A. Uh let's go ahead and mark that
with a probe. Let's mark that as a. Okay. And now
we've got to have B. B is a little bit trickier.
Um, where am I gonna Well, let's start with B E.
Let's put B an easy. Let's make B Let's make B be
here. Okay. So, then let's put the contact of B,
the probe B right there. So, now I have B. Now,
the key thing is I've got to get this this B
up to this second um POS gate. So, I could do
a lot of things here. I could route it up here and
route it over there. Or I could route it over here
and then route it down to here. So, I think I'm
going to come through here. So, you're going to
see something. I'm going to take this polysilicon.
And in a real circuit, you might find that this is
kind of Oh, look what I can do because when I make
this polyilicon come across the metal right there,
it's not actually connected. And then look no
yikes. I got to erase it because I made a kind of
a blob. I spilled some I spilled some polysilicon.
So now I can actually connect this together. Wow.
I think that looks pretty easy at this point. Did
it work? So I have my I have my A connected to one
of the P pos transistors and one of the NMOS
transistors and then I have my B connected to
one of the NMOS transistors and one of the POS
transistors. I have a feeling that it is right
and I think if we look at our assignment we're
supposed to make a Q as the output. So let's put
another probe here on the output Q. So I could run
the autograder. I think I got it. I think I made
one that's pretty good here. But one of the things
I do to test these things is um Oh, I didn't mean
to put that via there. Put a VCC there. So now
I can see that I put a plus in the A area and it
stops the POS, but it does transmit. But then I
have to put like let's put a VCC where the B is
now. Oh, I'm missing a V. See how the the voltage
comes here in the one and it hits this overlap. I
got to put a via there because it doesn't really
touch. Boop. So now I think we got it. So we got
um A is one and B is one and the output is zero
which is good. So we can keep testing it. I just
test it by popping a ground in here. So now we
have a is zero and b is one and the output is one
which is what it's supposed to be because it's
a gate. So I'm going to go back to putting the
probes in. So you notice how I can just kind of
overwrite this stuff. So there's a and I got the
probe b now. Now I can actually start the grater.
I think it'll go through all the combinations in
the truth table and it will tell us if it likes
the circuit that we built. So let's go ahead
check for the A, B, and Q probes. They seem to be
there. Test. Let's set A to zero and B to zero.
And is the output one? A is zero. B is zero.
Outputs one. Yes, it is. Set A to zero and B to
one. Is the output zero? A. Oh, no. The output is
supposed to be one in that case. Yep. So this is a
And then if we do a to one and
B to zero, the output is one.
And then if we set them both to to one, the
output is zero, which it's a NAND gate. And
so we finished and away we go. So there we did.
We took and viewed this image and made ourselves
the gate by laying it out. And again, I
tend to start by laying transistors out,
but you got to give yourself a little space as you
lay these things out and put them together. Now,
I've built them a few times. The first few
that you're going to build are going to be a
little tricky, but it's very satisfying when you
get them finished. So, I hope you enjoyed this
walkthrough for computer architecture on the
building of a gate using a VLSI design tool.